{
  "reference_number": "12454",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The time to act is long past. We have known this would be a problem in the early part of the 20th century..(Ref \"World's in the Making\"\n Svante Arrhenius Pub 1908) If we are seen to be making a stand, other countries will follow."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The unknown is how dramatic and potentially catastrophic will be the effect of water as a greenhouse gas in the role in positive\n\n feedback. Understanding this role is crucial to prevent a \"runaway\" global warming.(The atmosphere being able to hold more\n water(gas) as the atmosphere warms.)"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Should include exports that have GHG emissions in another country. A serious look at air travel. To meet targets, dairy and tourism\n would be serious affected. This has to be planned for. Forest planting has to be considered carefully. What species? Will they cope\n with change? Will they be harvested for timber or simply destroyed by fire later, either deliberately or accidentally (Christchurch)?"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It will be a miracle if we reach zero carbon or carbon neutral (slightly different) by 2050. If we were to reach our goal before 2050,\n\n that's a bonus.However, if by 2030 the predictions are worst than expected, we now may have to revise the target to an earlier date.\n (and we will all be riding bikes!)"
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Yes, but only if the climate is becoming more chaotic and we have to move the target to say 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "To keep the public and business well informed. Work together with other like minded countries to share ideas on the best road\nforward. Don't treat fixing the problem as a tax. If the general population are not on side the goals are unlikely to be reached."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Unless the NZ ETS is well managed I doubt it will be effective. Trading emissions is just handing the problem around. An excuse for\nsomeone else to emit GHG."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However, the country almost has to be put on a war footing. The time to act was many years ago. These measures may be too little\nand to late. Unfortunately climate change can be so difficult to predict and a hard sell as it is for most people, way in the future. We\n\nprobably only have a slim chance to fix the problem globally and it will be a hard sell."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is a serious global issue possibly resulting in serious food shortages and population dislocation. There are still a few skeptics out\n\nthere. Government must get everyone on board. As a country we must set an example."
    }
  ]
}
